<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sudheer Ganisetti</title>
    <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Sudheer Ganisetti</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/images/icon_huc51928fe27f661b4ab334eff98f193d1_363360_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Sudheer Ganisetti</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing glass-forming ability and mechanical properties of barium-calcium-aluminate glasses through ZnO inclusion</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_08/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deciphering the controlling factors for phase transitions in zeolitic imidazolate frameworks</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_11/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Functional Applications of H-Glass Embedded with Stable Plasmonic Gold Nanoislands</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_09/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The origin of deformation induced topological anisotropy in silica glass</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_07/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elucidating the influence of structure and Ag&#43;-Na&#43; ion-exchange on crack-resistance and ionic conductivity of Na3Al1.8Si1.65P1.8O12 glass electrolyte</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_06/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Scientist with Python Track</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/accomplishments/17_datacamp_datascience/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/accomplishments/17_datacamp_datascience/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ionic Conductivity of NASICON based Na3Al2P3O12 Glass Electrolytes − Role of Charge Compensators</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effect of Vanadium Oxide on the Structure and Li-Ion Conductivity of Lithium Silicate Glasses</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/project/05_heart_disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/project/05_heart_disease/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Complete SQL Bootcamp 2021</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/accomplishments/16_udemy_sql_bootcamp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/accomplishments/16_udemy_sql_bootcamp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Complete Machine Learning &amp; Data Science Bootcamp 2021</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/accomplishments/15_udemy_data_science_bootcamp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/accomplishments/15_udemy_data_science_bootcamp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elucidating the effect of CaF2 on structure, biocompatibility and antibacterial properties of S53P4 glass</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_03/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_03/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elucidating the formation of Al–NBO bonds, Al–O–Al linkages and clusters in alkaline-earth aluminosilicate glasses based on molecular dynamics simulations</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_02/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_02/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Policy</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/privacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add your privacy policy here and set &lt;code&gt;draft: false&lt;/code&gt; to publish it. Otherwise, delete this file if you don&amp;rsquo;t need it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terms</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/terms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/terms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add your terms here and set &lt;code&gt;draft: false&lt;/code&gt; to publish it. Otherwise, delete this file if you don&amp;rsquo;t need it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structure and Crystallization of Alkaline-Earth Aluminosilicate Glasses: Prevention of the Alumina-Avoidance Principle</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/publication/publication_01/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiscale Modelling</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/project/01_multiscale_modelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/project/01_multiscale_modelling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3&gt; Multiscale Modelling of the Influence of Oxygen on Structure and Cohesion of &amp;Sigma;5 Symmetrical Tilt Grain Boundary in Molybdenum &lt;/h3&gt;
The brittle fracture of real materials originates from the atomistic mechanisms like sequential bond breaking, which leads to the crack initiation, propagation and finally to material damage in the macro scale. Predicting such material failures, and there by analyzing mechanical properties are challenging as well as complex tasks. To achieve these challenges, it often require the knowledge from atomic level to macroscopic level, therefore, scale bridging of different length scales is necessary.  
&lt;p&gt;In this work, we have investigated how the oxygen and carbon impurities influence fracture behavior when segregated to the ∑5 symmetrical tilt grain boundary in molybdenum.
Mechanical properties such as work of separation and theoretical strength were computed based on the calculations performed at different length scales, i.e, from atomistic length scales to macroscopic length scales. Ab-initio method based on density functional theory were used for the atomistic scale calculations, and finite element method based on cohesive traction separation laws were used for the continuum scale calculations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key idea to this approach is the recasting of the atomistic results within the frame  work of a continuum cohesive zone model. The traction separation laws were derived by performing the tensile tests using the first principle calculations. The effective cohesive zone elements were then defined, and placed along all the possible fracture interfaces in a finite element mesh. Finite element simulations were then used to study the failure properties at the macroscopic length scales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Density functional theory based total energy and electronic structure calculations were performed with the Vienna Ab-initio Simulation Package (VASP). The electron exchange and correlation interactions were approximated by the generalized gradient approximation, and electron ion interactions were treated with the ultrasoft pseudo potentials for 80 atom supercell. The grain boundary energy, work of separation, and theoretical strengths were calculated for various oxygen impurity concentrations, i.e, from 0 to 4 oxygen atoms per grain boundary. It was found that oxygen shows an embrittling effect in the molybdenum grain boundary, see the above figure. However, when carbon is placed along with oxygen, the embrittling effect of the oxygen was compensated partially by the carbon atoms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phase Field</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/project/02_phase_field/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/project/02_phase_field/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3&gt; Building of Bridges using Phase Field Method &lt;/h3&gt;
In civil engineering, shape optimization is necessary to build strong structures according to their structural performances. Most structural optimizations take into account  structural performances such as stress, mass, deformation. In this work, we have partially optimized the shape of a bridge which connects two banks of a river. To build the strong bridge to withstand high mechanical loads, we have used the technique of growing high strength material in the place of high stress areas, and filled the remaining place with a soft and low weight material such as ‘air’. The ‘growth’ of the high strength material in high stress fields has done based on the Phase Field method. The key idea used is the replacement of actual shape optimization problem by a two phase material distribution problem. The two materials used are the high contrast in their strength properties, a matrix material and a high strength material in the form of inclusions. Phase field  method was used to find the motion of optimized shape boundaries. To solve the multicomponent phase field equations, an open source library called ‘OpenPhase’ developed at Prof. Ingo Steinbach department, ICAMS, has been used. 
&lt;p&gt;The above figure shows: (a) Initialization of different areas of a bridge with different phases, (b) A partially optimized arc shape of the bridge (every pole has the same eigenstrain)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A C++ code has been written to initialize the model with different phases representing different material properties in the OpenPhase source code. The driving force is assigned to  the inclusion material in such a way that it grows in the region where the stresses are high. From the results, we observed that the shape of the optimized structure looks like a semicircle arc shape. Here, we have not taken the idle values of the input parameters for the surrounding environments like water and air etc., so the arc shape is not fully formed. Some more work has to be done to complete the arc shape bridge. However, based on the primary results, we have showcased that the structures can be optimized with Phase Fields using the OpenPhase code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DFT</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/project/03_diffusion_of_carbon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/project/03_diffusion_of_carbon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3&gt; Diffusion of Carbon in High Silicon Steel &lt;/h3&gt;
Many important phenomena in materials science involve diffusion of impurities. It is well known that diffusion of carbon in metals typically occurs via an interstitial mechanism, which can be strongly affected by the presence of other alloying elements. The interstitial diffusion of carbon controls the phase transformation in steel and therefore the resulting microstructure and mechanical properties. 
Density functional theory (DFT) based total energy and electronic structure calculations were performed with the Vienna Ab-Initio Simulation Package (VASP) to understand how silicon affects the the diffusion path of carbon in steel. The electron exchange and correlation interactions were approximated by the Generalized Gradient Approximation (GGA), and electron ion interactions were treated with Projector Augmented Wave (PAW) potentials. 
Through this work, we have studied two cases. In the first case, the energy barriers of one octahedral site to another octahedral site in the diffusion path of carbon atom away from the silicon atom in bcc Fe were computed, and these values were compared with the energy barriers of the pure bcc Fe system. In the second case, we have studied the possibilities of diffusion paths of C from octahedral position of one of the faces of a unit cell to the octahedral site of the neighboring face of the same unit cell. 
&lt;p&gt;Fig (a) shows a supercell consisting of two unit cells. Silicon is substitutionally added to the body centred atom of the first unitcell, and carbon diffuses away from the silicon atom through interstitial positions 1_Oct, 2_Tetra, 3_Oc, etc., as shown in the fig (a). The fig  (b) shows the total relaxed energy of the system of 53 Fe atoms with one substitutionally added Si and one interstitial C atom along the diffusing path of C from 1st octahedral site to  the 7th Octahedral site away from the Si. After finding the formation energies and energy  barriers, we conclude that the silicon traps the carbon atom to its second nearest neighbor tetrahedral position or third nearest neighbor octahedral position. It was also revealed that the diffusion path of C from Octahedral site of one face to the octahedral site of the neighboring face is possible only through the tetrahedral interstitial site even in the presence of Si.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monte Carlo Simulations</title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/project/04_monte_carlo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/project/04_monte_carlo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Monte Carlo method was used to tackle the global optimization problem of molecular structure. A Fortran code was developed to optimize a 13 atom molecular structure. Molecular simulations are very convenient to get insight into the structure and thermal behavior of small atomic clusters. Atomic structures are finite size aggregates containing between a few and millions of particles. Due to their small dimensions, their theoretical study faces serious difficulties. The most properties exhibit a strong dependence on the number of atoms. These difficulties actually begin with the unoptimized structure, from which other characteristics will develop. Predicting the temperature where the cluster changes phase also requires simulations. By the use of numerical simulation method, we can achieve phase transition easily. Metropolis Monte Carlo method was chosen to sample the configuration space for structural  optimization, and for simulating thermal equilibrium in a small Lennard-Jones cluster. Simulated Annealing technique stands as one of the most general and efficient ways  of addressing the global optimization problem. Simulated annealing essentially consists of  cooling slowly. The initial temperature, cooling schedule and total simulation length are the  few but important parameters of a simulated annealing optimization. Starting from a random  atomic configuration, the MC simulation is carried out following the metropolis acceptance rule, and after some number of steps the temperature was decreased. In this way, the  most stable configuration of a 13 atom cluster was found by energy minimization.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/admin/config.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sudheerganisetti.github.io/admin/config.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
